School of Computing Science fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
School of Computing Science fonds
1970 - 1999
F-93
3.63 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
DATE RANGE Predominant dates of the fonds are 1970 - 1991. Only three files contain post-1991 material and these are comprised of a series containing committee records (1992-1994), program brochures (1997), and a research report (1999).
School of Computing Science
The School of Computing Science began in 1973 as a Program in the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies. Courses were based on a single-track universal curriculum that focused on the interdisciplinary aspects of computing science, featuring a core of mainstream computing topics together with a techniques sector dealing with applications. Core courses were taught by regular Computing Science faculty while the techniques courses were taught by faculty from other disciplines. The Program offered undergraduate courses leading to a minor, major or honors degree in Computing Science.
In 1975 the Computing Science Program became a department, with nine tenure track faculty. That same year the School began a Co-operative Education Program that continues to place students in 4 and 8 month work-term positions with local, national, and international industries. In 1979 a graduate program was initiated with the approval of both M.Sc. and Ph.D. programs and the first Ph.D. students were admitted in 1983. In 1985, Computing Science joined the newly formed Faculty of Applied Science and became known as the School of Computing Science. The role of departmental Chairman was renamed Director and in 1989 the School was moved to its current space in the Applied Sciences Building.
Over the years, the School's curriculum has developed in response to changing computer technology and faculty research interests focussing on computer theory, hardware and software systems, multimedia applications, databases, and artificial intelligence. The School now offers a general program leading to a B.Sc. and B.A. degree with major or honors in Computing Science and specialist programs leading to a B.Sc degree with a major in Computing Science. It also contributes to a wide variety of programs that combine studies in other academic disciplines. Formal joint programs consist of Joint Major in Information Systems in Business Administration and Computing Science; Joint Major in Molecular Biology and Biochemistry and Computing Science; Mathematics and Computing Science Joint Honors Program; Cognitive Science Program (in cooperation with the Departments of Linguistics, Philosophy, and Psychology); and the Management and Systems Science Program (in cooperation with the Department of Mathematics, the Department of Economics, and the Faculty of Business Administration).
The school also offers a minor program that can be taken in conjunction with other major or honors programs or a general degree program. Other programs include Digital Systems Design Honors (established in 1981), a Bachelor of General Studies Minor, the Second Degree Program, and the Certificate Program that provides part and full time students an opportunity to obtain an understanding of the fundamentals of computers and programming without specializing in Computing Science. The School continues to offer a non-credit summer Computer Institute for high school students and teachers.
Current research computing facilities at the School include over 300 networked workstations, file servers, CPU servers and other specialized systems. Undergraduate computing facilities include the Computing Science Instructional Lab (CSIL) that provides computers for students to do coursework assigned to particular software platforms. The School of Computing Science operates several interconnected Local Area Networks in cooperation with other schools in the Faculty of Applied Sciences and the Centre for Systems Science (CSS). The Laboratory for Computer and Communications Research (LCCR) is a separate lab operated in cooperation with the Department of Communications. Established in 1982, the LCCR promotes inquiry into the problems of computing and communication research; fosters cooperative efforts between the university, industry and government agencies; and sponsors distinguished visitors.
published
Full
Published
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records relating to the activities of the School and its predecessors. Activities and events documented include the evolution of the School's structure, functions and governance; deliberation of committees; correspondence of the Director with staff, faculty, university departments and external organizations; grants, scholarships, and research projects; computing laboratories and facility files; curriculum development and course files.
Records include budget and financial working papers; correspondence and reports; meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers; policies and procedures; course proposals and outlines; lecture notes and planning materials; and publications including course guides, brochures, student society newsletters and annual reports.
The arrangement of the fonds into series and subseries was provided by the Archivist in July 2004. Series 7, subseries 2 (Curriculum files) is based on the creator's original groupings. Other series were established by the archivist to provide structure to the bulk of "general subject files" transferred by the creator.
Delgrande, James; Liestman, Arthur L.; Hobson, Rick F.; Weinkam, James J.; Sterling, Ted; Cercone, Nick; Luk, Wo-Shun
All accessions have been processed as of July 2004. Further accruals are expected.
The records were transferred to the Archives over four accessions between 1999 and 2003.
For records relating to the School's tenure in the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, see fonds F-23 (subseries 23-3-4) and for tenure in the Faculty of Applied Sciences, see fonds F-154 (not processed to date).
The fonds includes records containing personal information. Access to these files may be restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- School history and structure files, 1971 - 1986; F-93-1; 9 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the evolution of the School, its internal organization and mandate, scope of activities, and reorganization as part of the Faculty of Applied Science in 1985. Activities, events and topics documented include program planning in the early 1970's, departmental profile and formal review.
  Records include correspondence, reports, planning documents, notes and working papers.
  This series was created by the archivist in July 2004 to provide structure to the creator's general subject files. Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  Access to files containing personal information may be restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review some files may be restricted in accordance with the FOI/POP Act. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Computer Science Program, 1971; F-93-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Graduate Studies, 1982 - 1984; F-93-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
  - Faculty of Applied Science - general, 1984 - 1986; F-93-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
  - Department profile and reorganization, 1982 - 1984; F-93-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
  - Review of the new Computer Science program at SFU, 1973; F-93-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
- Administrative files, 1975 - 1989; F-93-2; 19 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the administration of the School office and management of relations with non-academic employees. Activities, events and topics documented include capital budget planning; search for School chairman; enrollment and registration issues; fundraising; faculty workshops and retreats; the appointment of Teaching Assistants and Sessional Instructors; space requirements and the move to the Applied Sciences Building.
  Records include budgets, correspondence and reports, capital equipment requests, planning documents, notes and working papers.
  - Applied Sciences Building, 1985 - 1986; F-93-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
  - Budget, 1980 - 1983; F-93-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Budget, 1982 - 1986; F-93-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
    Open
  - Capital budget, 1985 - 1988; F-93-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Capital budget, 1987 - 1989; F-93-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Computing Science search for chairman, 1980 - 1982; F-93-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Conferences, 1985 - 1986; F-93-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Directors file, 1983 - 1987; F-93-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Departmental enrollment issues, 1981 - 1987; F-93-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Equipment budget, 1980 - 1983; F-93-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Fundraising / Donations, 1981 - 1985; F-93-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Market Differential / Salaries, 1980 - 1985; F-93-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Registration / Course planning, 1984 - 1985; F-93-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Registration priorities, 1985; F-93-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Gabriola workshop, 1980 - 1981; F-93-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 93-2)
  - Retreat / departmental workshop, 1981 - 1989; F-93-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Retreat, 1988; F-93-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Space, 1975 - 1978; F-93-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Teaching Assistants and sessional appointments, 1981 - 1983; F-93-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
- Committee files, 1972 - 1994; F-93-3; 85 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to meetings and deliberations of departmental, faculty, university, and external committees in which faculty or representatives from Computing Science participated. Departmental activities, events and topics documented include meetings; faculty search, hiring, and tenure deliberations; computing facilities; curriculum development; undergraduate and graduate programs; and hardware and software acquisition. Faculty records include minutes of the Faculty of Applied Science Executive Committee and the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies Executive Committee. University-wide records consist of minutes and papers from committees such as academic planning, computer policy and planning, and research policy. External committee records include minutes and papers of the British Columbia Computers in Education Committee and the Canadian Computer Science Department Chairmen Committee.
  Records include meeting agendas, minutes and supporting documents; correspondence; reports; policies and procedures; program revisions and course proposals; and working papers.
  Note that in the case of departmental committees, the files constitute the original, authoritative records of those committees. In the case of non-departmental committees (faculty, university and external), however, the School did not typically function as the official record-keeper or custodian of the committee's original records. Accordingly, these files document the School's participation in the committees (correspondence and copies of committee records) rather than representing the authoritative record of those committees.
  This series was created by the archivist in July 2004 to provide structure to the creator's general subject files. Each committee has been assigned a separate sub-series. Committees have been grouped into the following types: Departmental, Faculty, University and External. Within each sub-series, files have been arranged alphabetically.
  - Committees - general files, 1976 - 1986; F-93-3-1; 2 cm of textual records
    - General / Departmental Committee membership, 1976 - 1980; F-93-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
    - Departmental Committee membership, 1982 - 1986; F-93-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Academic Dishonesty Committee files, 1981 - 1987; F-93-3-2; 1 cm of textual records
    - Academic Dishonesty Committee, 1981 - 1987; F-93-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Ad Hoc Computing Policy and Planning Committee files, 1983; F-93-3-3; 2 cm of textual records
    - Ad Hoc Computing Policy and Planning Committee, vol. 1, 1983; F-93-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
    - Ad Hoc Computing Policy and Planning Committee, vol. 2, 1983; F-93-3-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Chairman Search Committee files, 1979; F-93-3-4; 1 cm of textual records
    - Chairman Search Committee, 1979; F-93-3-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computer Assisted Instruction (CAI) Committee files, 1973 - 1974; F-93-3-5; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computer Assisted Instruction (CAI) Committee, 1973 - 1974; F-93-3-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computer Graphics Committee files, 1975; F-93-3-6; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computer Graphics Committee, 1975; F-93-3-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computing Facilities Committee files, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-7; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computing Facilities Committee, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computing Projects in the Arts and Sciences Committee files, 1974 - 1975; F-93-3-8; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computing Projects in the Arts and Sciences Committee, 1974 - 1975; F-93-3-8-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computing Science / Computer Center Liaison Committee files, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-9; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computing Science / Computing Centre Liaison Committee, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-9-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-3)
  - Departmental Computing Science Program Selection Committee files, 1977 - 1978; F-93-3-10; 1 cm of textual records
    - Computing Science Program Selection Committee, 1977 - 1978; F-93-3-10-0-1
  - Departmental Curriculum Committtee files, 1972 - 1977; F-93-3-11; 3 cm of textual records
    - Curriculum Development Committee, 1972; F-93-3-11-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
    - Curriculum Development Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-93-3-11-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
  - Departmental Curriculum - Undergraduate Committee files, 1977 - 1981; F-93-3-12; 3 cm of textual records
    - Curriculum - Undergraduate Committee, vol. 1, 1977 - 1981; F-93-3-12-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
    - Curriculum - Undergraduate Committee, vol. 2, 1977 - 1981; F-93-3-12-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
  - Departmental Director's Committee files, 1983 - 1984; F-93-3-13; 1 cm of textual records
    - Director's Meetings, 1983 - 1984; F-93-3-13-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
  - Departmental Director's Search Committee files, 1986; F-93-3-14; 1 cm of textual records
    - Director's Search Committee, 1986; F-93-3-14-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
  - Departmental Faculty Search Committee files, 1977 - 1988; F-93-3-15; 5 cm of textual records
    - Faculty Search Committee, 1977 - 1985; F-93-3-15-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
    - Faculty Search Committee, 1987 - 1988; F-93-3-15-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-4)
    - Faculty Search - position authorization, vol. 1, 1980 - 1984; F-93-3-15-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
    - Faculty Search - position authorization, vol. 2, 1980 - 1984; F-93-3-15-0-4 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee files, 1976 - 1980; F-93-3-16; 1 cm of textual records
    - Graduate Studies Committee, 1976 - 1980; F-93-3-16-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Hardware / Software Committee files, 1976 - 1980; F-93-3-17; 1 cm of textual records
    - Hardware / Software Committee, 1976 - 1980; F-93-3-17-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Joint Computing / Math Committee files, 1975; F-93-3-18; 1 cm of textual records
    - Joint Computing / Mathematics Committee, 1975; F-93-3-18-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Junior Chair (NSERC) Search Committee files, 1992 - 1994; F-93-3-19; 1 cm of textual records
    - Junior Chair (NSERC) Search Committee, 1992 - 1994; F-93-3-19-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Library Committee files, 1976 - 1983; F-93-3-20; 1 cm of textual records
    - Library Committee, 1976 - 1983; F-93-3-20-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Management Committee files, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-21; 1 cm of textual records
    - Management Meetings, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-21-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
  - Departmental Meeting files, 1974 - 1986; F-93-3-22; 12 cm of textual records
    - Departmental Meetings, 1974 - 1976; F-93-3-22-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1977; F-93-3-22-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-5)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1978 - 1979; F-93-3-22-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1980 - 1981; F-93-3-22-0-4 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1982; F-93-3-22-0-5 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1983; F-93-3-22-0-6 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1984; F-93-3-22-0-7 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1985; F-93-3-22-0-8 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1986; F-93-3-22-0-9 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
  - Departmental Steering Committee files, 1972 - 1976; F-93-3-23; 3 cm of textual records
    - Steering Committee - correspondence on committee appointments, 1974 - 1976; F-93-3-23-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
    - Steering Committee - minutes and meetings, 1972 - 1975; F-93-3-23-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-6)
  - Departmental Teaching Assistants Committee files, 1975 - 1978; F-93-3-24; 2 cm of textual records
    - Teaching Assistants Committee, 1975 - 1978; F-93-3-24-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
  - Departmental Tenure Committee files, 1976 - 1989; F-93-3-25; 5 cm of textual records
    - Tenure Committee, 1976 - 1982; F-93-3-25-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
    - Tenure Committee, 1983 - 1986; F-93-3-25-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
    - Tenure Committee, 1988 - 1989; F-93-3-25-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Studies Committee files, 1981 - 1984; F-93-3-26; 2 cm of textual records
    - Undergraduate Studies Committee, 1981 - 1984; F-93-3-26-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
  - Faculty of Applied Sciences Executive Committee files, 1985 - 1987; F-93-3-27; 5 cm of textual records
    Faculty of Applied Sciences Executive Committee
    - Faculty of Applied Science Executive Committee - minutes and correspondence, 1985; F-93-3-27-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
    - Faculty of Applied Science Executive Committee - minutes and correspondence, vol. 1, 1987; F-93-3-27-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
    - Faculty of Applied Science Executive Committee - minutes and correspondence, vol. 2, 1987; F-93-3-27-0-3 (Archival box - standard 93-7)
  - Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies Ad Hoc Computing Policy and Planning Committee files, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-28; 2 cm of textual records
    Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies. Ad Hoc Computing Policy and Planning Committee
    - Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies Ad Hoc Computing Planning and Policy Committee, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-28-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Academic Planning Committee files, 1974 - 1976; F-93-3-29; 2 cm of textual records
    Academic Planning Committee
    - Academic Planning Committee, 1974 - 1976; F-93-3-29-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Ad Hoc Committee on Academic Computing files, 1973 - 1974; F-93-3-30; 2 cm of textual records
    Ad Hoc Committee on Academic Computing
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Academic Computing, 1973 - 1974; F-93-3-30-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Chairmen's Meeting files, 1980 - 1983; F-93-3-31; 2 cm of textual records
    University Chairmen's Committee
    - University Chairmen's Meetings, 1980 - 1983; F-93-3-31-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Computing Committee files, 1972 - 1973; F-93-3-32; 2 cm of textual records
    University Computing Committee
    - University Computing Committee, 1972 - 1973; F-93-3-32-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Computing Policy Committee files, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-33; 4 cm of textual records
    Computing Policy Committee
    - Computing Policy Committee, vol. 1, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-33-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
    - Computing Policy Committee, vol. 2, 1981 - 1983; F-93-3-33-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-8)
  - University - Dean's Advisory Committee files, 1981 - 1984; F-93-3-34; 3 cm of textual records
    Dean's Advisory Committee
    - Dean's Advisory Committee, 1981 - 1982; F-93-3-34-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
    - Dean's Advisory Committee, 1983 - 1984; F-93-3-34-0-2 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - Dean's Search Committee files, 1981 - 1982; F-93-3-35; 1 cm of textual records
    Dean's Search Committee
    - Dean's Search Committee, 1981 - 1982; F-93-3-35-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - Engineering Program Planning Committee files, 1981; F-93-3-36; 1 cm of textual records
    Engineering Program Planning Committee
    - Engineering Program Planning Committee, 1981; F-93-3-36-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - President's Advisory Committee on Computing Science files, 1984 - 1985; F-93-3-37; 1 cm of textual records
    President's Advisory Committee on Computing Science
    - President's Advisory Committee on Computing Science / Computing Advisory Committee, 1984 - 1985; F-93-3-37-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - President's Advisory Committee on the University Library files, 1984; F-93-3-38; 1 cm of textual records
    President's Advisory Committee on the University Library
    - President's Advisory Committee on University Library, 1984; F-93-3-38-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities (PACUP) files, 1984; F-93-3-39; 1 cm of textual records
    President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities
    - President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities (PACUP), 1984; F-93-3-39-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - Research Council Committee files, 1985; F-93-3-40; 1 cm of textual records
    University Research Council Committee
    - University Research Council Committee, 1985; F-93-3-40-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)
  - University - Senate Committee on Academic Planning (SCAP) files, 1973 - 1984; F-93-3-41; 1 cm of textual records
    Senate Committee on University Priorities
    - Senate Committee on Academic Planning (SCAP), 1973 - 1984; F-93-3-41-0-1 (Archival box - standard 93-9)